[Music]
hello hello everyone welcome to the
latest episode of the ask a budget show
i hope you're all doing very well
uh as you know today we are discussing
uh science
and uh that's what we will discuss so
let me first take a look at who all is
there
and greet you all so i can see anshuman
yuvraj
jatin
harshwardhan
deepak crazy brain umbrella corporation
priyanshi
samarth pratham
dar jatin rajat
and lots of other people
good evening good day to all of you
with that said i will get right into the
questions as always a lot of questions
so let's see what we have for today
what are today's questions let's go with
question number one
question number one is by tejas they
just says
why is zero not equal to one please
answer it in a way that viewers like me
won't fall asleep
um
i could offer you a mathematical proof
that zero is not equal to one but how do
i
prove it in a way that
that you won't fall asleep
uh so
how many of me do you see right now how
many of widgets do you see right now you
see one a widget right
and how many objects do you see now
how many this is zero
you can see zero objects now
now it's one
now it's zero
magic
so that
i hope
proves
that 0 is not equal to 1
there you have it that is your
non-mathematical but physical proof that
0 is not equal to 1.
hope that makes sense and i hope that it
did not make you fall asleep
okay next question
what's the next question
the next question is by swapnil
uh
how was a big heart transplant in a
human
made possible recently and why did it
fail
so soon
right so people have been uh
trying to have been testing out various
ways of implanting uh
organs
from other species into humans in order
to overcome the human organ shortage so
many people have organs that fail in old
age or because of whatever reason hearts
and lungs and kidneys and livers and
other organs yes
so there is a high there's a high demand
for organs
and of course the only way to
to acquire organs is from somebody who
unfortunately passes away and the organs
are still intact yeah or somebody who's
brain dead and whose family decides to
donate the organs for so for somebody
else's benefit that sort of thing
but such people are very scarce
typically when a person unfortunately
passes away the body decomposes very
fast unless you're in a medical
environment where the organs can quickly
be harvested and saved the organs will
go to waste that's how it is
unfortunately so a better alternative if
it is possible is to find a way of
transplanting a
non-human organs into humans
but that obviously has lots of problems
right because first of all the main
problem in organ transplants is
rejection our immune systems
know what is our own tissue and what is
non what is tissue that doesn't belong
to us uh they understand that our
our immune system understands that even
if you get a transplant from another
human being your immune system will
immediately know that this is not your
tissue it's from somebody else and it's
going to attack that it's going to
regard that as a foreign invasive force
it's going to go ahead and try to
destroy it and the immune system is very
good at doing this it typically destroys
organs very rapidly that are that are
transplanted from another another person
into you or into a donor into a
recipient from a donor to a recipient so
to go to so this is called organ
rejection it happens very rapidly and to
overcome this problem
typically you give immunosuppressant
drugs to the recipient which suppresses
the immune system which has all kinds of
other problems so it's it's a tight rope
it's a tight rope act that you have to
do you should not suppress the system
immune system so much that that the
person will fall prey to any kind of
illness and die from that but also the
immune system the immune system should
not destroy the organ that you the
recipient needs in order to stay alive
so uh typically you give certain drugs
that suppress the immune system to a
certain extent but uh
keep the person reasonably healthy right
uh it's usually a cocktail of
immunosuppressive drugs and all that
so that's when you have a human to human
transplant there's this new process
called xenotransplantation so it's from
one species to another species now
typically pig organs are quite similar
to human organs and that's why the
people have been trying have been
exploring the possibility scientists and
doctors have been exploring the
possibility of transplanting uh porcine
organs into humans xenotransplantation
so initially they did tests on baboons
baboons are a species of monkey
they're not apes they are monkeys right
yeah
so people uh when scientists tested uh
transplantation of organs from pigs into
baboons it worked reasonably well then
what they did was they tested the uh
the connection of pig organs like
kidneys essentially i believe to brain
dead human beings so people whose brains
have stopped functioning they're dead
they're in the vegetative state they
have no chance of recovery
so that sort of thing was tested out and
it's it seemed to work well uh the the
kidneys of pigs were
attached
to these human bodies that were no
longer viable
uh
they were brain dead and the kidneys i
believe functioned reasonably well they
functioned well
as per expectations they produced urine
and all that so that worked now in
january 2022 this year there was this
person this elderly person in the u.s
who
uh who had a heart that was failing that
person was guaranteed to die he had no
he had no way out and he was not
eligible for whatever reason for a uh
for a human transplant
so the authorities gave the go-ahead for
a
xenotransplantation procedure
a big heart would be implanted in that
person
and this was not any just any regular
pig it was uh there's this company i
don't know which what's the name of the
company you can look it up
which uh engineers pigs that are that
whose genes have been edited
so what is done is that the genome of
these pigs is edited in such a way that
you implant some humans human genes in
there
and you remove some some pig genes so
that kind of
tricks the human body which will receive
the pig organ into believing that this
could possibly be a human organ so it's
like stealth mode you activate stealth
mode and you implant the organ in the
recipient
so that sort of uh procedure was done
they raised these pigs that have these
mixed genetics whose genes were edited
and then obviously one of these pigs
would have to be sacrificed and you
remove the heart that's how it's done
it's sad but that's how it is you remove
the heart and so
one of these big hearts was implanted in
this
person in the u.s i believe in january
this year 2021
and it went well
yeah the person
woke up from the operation the the heart
was beating
as well as could be expected
and
and the person survived two two months i
believe before he passed away and
everything was going well but then
suddenly the person started falling uh
ill he was not well
and uh
what they discovered is that it was not
that the
organ was rejected
they had given a cocktail of
immunosuppressive drugs i think on two
occasions to this person after the
transplant was done
and
his immune system was not attacking the
big organ the pig heart it was not
rejecting it what happened is that there
was some virus
some big virus
that was present in this organ in the
tissue in the heart tissue i think it
was called the porcine
cytomegalovirus or something like that
though i may have got it wrong that's
what this virus was called now they had
engineered the pigs and they had given
the guarantee this company that there
would be no viruses but clearly they
messed up so this organ
this heart
had that virus the porcine
cytomegalovirus
now
this
virus is not something that typically
infects human cells it infects pork
pig tissue
now in inside a pig these viruses are
prevalent and the pig's immune system
ensures that the uh viruses are
suppressed and they don't create any
trouble
but when you remove the organ from a pig
pig's body you implant it into a human
body
the human body has a human immune system
not a pig porcine immune system and
that's why the uh
the viruses start proliferating that's
what seems to have happened
so when they finally did the autopsy of
the organ and all that they found that
there was an unbelievably high high
amount of virus in there
and that's possibly what had caused the
degradation of the organ it became uh it
stopped functioning as it should have it
it's it beca the the walls became
thickened and and more stiff stiffer
than what you would expect and something
like that right you can look up exactly
what it was uh there's plenty of
articles about that
and uh so that's what happened so
there's a couple of reasons why this
could have happened first of all the
company messed up
the company that produced these pigs
had given a guarantee that there would
be no viruses but they messed up and
this virus was present in the tissue
and secondly the the immunosuppressive
drugs they had the doctors had given to
the person intravenous immunoglobulin or
whatever
it contained antibodies that
acted against pig cells
so not only was there the problem of the
virus but the uh the antibodies that
were given to the person the patient
acted against the pig cells and would
have possibly damaged the the heart
tissue in some way so there are a number
of reasons why
eventually the heart failed and the
person passed away
but it's not because of organ rejection
which is good news
this is good news first of all this
person was as good as dead he he
essentially had no hope of survival so
he was given he got another extra two
months of life eventually this this the
heart failed but it was not because of
organ rejection which is a significant
step forward
so if
these problems that arose could be
circumvented firstly by by ensuring that
the next
heart has no
on no such viruses and secondly you
don't give antibodies that act against
pig cells then possibly the next such
recipient would have a much longer life
and the heart would last much longer so
uh it's it's that's the latest news
human organ transplants have been going
have been happening for a very long time
i believe right now the heart transplant
from one human to another from a donor
to recipient is a reasonably routine
uh procedure reasonably routine
procedure it still has has risks now but
once the heart is implemented is
implanted i believe the average the
median uh life expectancy of a recipient
is about 15 years which is excellent
which is an excellent outcome so that's
where we are today but in the future i
believe xenotransplantation will be
worked will be researched upon much
further
in the future you may have such
procedures becoming more commonplace and
that would essentially if that can be
perfected and if you could achieve the
same kind of outcome 15 years median
lifestyle life expectancy after
transplantation that would be a massive
step forward that would be a massive
step forward and it would also it would
uh the problem that we face today is
this organ shortage there are so few
organs available and so many people who
need that so that could solve that
problem so that's where we are it's a
very interesting step forward obviously
it involves sacrificing the lives of
pigs but well that's unfortunately where
it is that's how it is
so that is the news that's what happened
that was the story of the pig transplant
that happened this year
a big heart transplant it failed but uh
it did not fail because of organ
rejection it failed because of other
reasons like i just outlined so that's
the story
okay washes says as per the abiogenic
petroleum origin theory most of the
earth's petroleum and natural gas
deposits may have been formed
inorganically like the methane and other
hydrocarbon fuel deposits on titan thus
the dinosaurs may not be the origin of
our fossil fuels how far is this is this
true
okay
so uh the mainstream theory the widely
accepted theory is that uh the origin of
petroleum is from the decomposition of
organic matter of
plant
etc matter the uh
abiogenic origin theory says that it
could have originated from non-leaving
materials
for instance
it is well known that various asteroids
and comets contain lots of organic
compounds right complex hydrocarbons
uh even amino acids
which is the which
amino acids are the are the basis of
life right are the basis of proteins
so it is so because of that evidence it
is speculated that maybe maybe the
petroleum and natural gas and fossil
fuels on the earth may could have could
possibly have had in
inorganic or a biogenetic abiogenic
origin
this theory is not a mainstream theory
it is not very well accepted uh
if you look at the various mechanisms in
which through which petroleum and fossil
fuels could form
the organic biogenic theory makes a lot
more sense
we know that life has been present on
this planet for billions of years
initially it was uh
unicellular then multiple cellular life
very simple life algae
you had algae all over the planet in the
oceans yeah and
so the theory is that when these algae
die
algae are typically unicellular plants
right so typically when these uh
organisms die
they would think
they would decompose but in certain
conditions when you have stagnant water
water that does not contain does not
have mixed oxygen oxygen dissolved in it
and when these algae die in stagnant
water they go to the bottom of the of
the pool of water maybe the the bottom
of the ocean where you have such
conditions and there is there are anoxic
conditions which means there is no
oxygen available there which means
decomposition cannot happen
then you could have a massive amount of
this organic material
that sinks to the bottom of an ocean of
the ocean eventually it goes underground
underground you have heat
heat under the surface of the under the
surface of the earth in the earth's
crust because of a number of factors
this heat uh catalyzes the production of
what eventually becomes petroleum
and depending on the on the depth below
the earth's surface you would either
have liquid petroleum you could have
kerogen i believe which is one stage
prior to the formation of petroleum or
or
uh
or oil
crude oil crude oil and if it is below a
certain depth then because of a process
called i believe cracking
you would have the the
formation of natural gas
so that this theory makes a lot more
sense given that there was this vast
proliferation of life
on the earth which is known from a large
amount of evidence yeah
so that theory makes a lot more sense we
know that
that titan has hydrocarbons
all over its surface in the atmosphere
and we know that the that hydrocarbons
and even amino acids are found on
asteroids and planets
and yet on earth the biogenic theory
makes a lot more sense and now
you're talking about dinosaur dinosaurs
are not the origin of fossil fuels it is
these
simple forms of life from the very early
phases of our planet's existence that
are
the origin that that are the source of
the origin of our fossil fuels whether
it is crude oil or or
or
gas
you know
natural gas
so that is
where we are that is the answer the a
biogenic petroleum origin theory does
not make a lot of sense the theory that
makes
way more sense is the biogenic origin
theory of petroleum and natural
gas okay
ira says
most unanswered question to me is that
why are oceans deep inside cold with
high pressure but as we go deeper
inland under the surface of the earth it
becomes hot
what is the reason behind this could you
please answer this and
explain it as well isn't this a very
interesting question fascinating
question you go below the ocean surface
the oceans get colder colder and colder
yeah
but
when you are when you go when you drill
below the surface of the earth in the
crust of the earth the deeper you go the
hotter it becomes
i mean for instance you go about 500
kilometers below the surface of the
earth
uh the temperature is almost 2000
degrees celsius almost
yeah you go 3000 kilometers below the
earth surface the temperature is around
3000 degrees celsius and the inner core
of the earth which is between five and
six thousand kilometers in depth has is
believed to have a temperature of about
seven thousand degrees celsius or kelvin
kelvin celsius almost the same right
so that is
that's how it is as you go deeper under
the earth surface the temperature rises
and yet under the oceans you go deeper
the temperature gets colder why is it so
so to understand why it is so we have to
understand what causes
the heat what is the source of the heat
under the under the earth's surface
so
firstly uh the the primary the the
oldest uh source of heat under the earth
surface is planetary accretion so our
solar system formed from a
a protoplanetary protosolar protostellar
disk
yeah which gave rise to the which gave
birth to the sun and the other planets
which are in existence around the sun
so that is number one
so that is the source of the uh that is
the first source of heat
uh am i visible or is there any problem
in the in the connection
is my image clear or is it blurred
that's the question i get the feeling
there may be some problem maybe not
maybe it's fine
is my image is my image visible properly
am i visible
it looks like i am visible all right
there may have been a brief network
issue
issue it seems to be good now all right
all right thank you for letting me know
okay so the the question is
is why are the oceans cold as we go deep
inside and why why is the surface why is
the earth why does the earth get hotter
as we drill deep inside
uh so the first source of heat is
residual heat from planetary accretion
the earth formed from very hot material
the protostellar disc
and there is a lot of heat left behind
from that as you go deeper into the
earth's surface
below the earth surface below the you
have you have several layers of the
earth surface you have the crust then
you have the mantle then you have the
magma layer then you have the outer core
and the inner core and as you go deeper
it's hotter because at the in the in the
interior of the earth you still have
this heat left over from the formation
of the solar system and of the earth so
that's number one the second source of
heat
in the surface of the in the in the
interiors of the earth is a radioactive
decay of radioactive isotopes nuclides
such as
uranium-238 uranium-235
thorium-232 potassium-40 and so on and
so forth there are a number of
radioactive elements that decay
radioactive decay occurs and this
radioactive decay gives off heat and
this contributes to the heat in the
interiors of the planet
so that
these are the two major reasons
why the interior of the earth gets
hotter as you go deeper inside firstly
residual heat from planetary accretion
secondly radioactive decay of
radioactive isotopes
none of neither of these two
sources of heat is present in the oceans
and that's why the oceans are much
colder and as you go deeper see
heat
rises to the top
hotter fluids
if you have a fluid which has a
temperature gradient you will always
find that the hotter part of the fluid
rises to the top and the colder one
sinks deeper deeper to the bottom
whether it is air
or whether it is uh of any any liquid
so therefore as you go deeper into the
ocean you will find colder and cooler
water so that's why as you go deeper
into the ocean
the water gets colder but as you go
deeper below the earth surface the
environment gets hotter
very good question i'm glad somebody
asked this
okay next question is by karan sharma
there is an idea in string theory that
the whole universe may be a hologram the
holographic principle suggests that we
all experience that
what we all experience every day in
three dimensions may really just be
information on a surface located at the
far just farthest reaches of our cosmos
what are your thoughts on this
do you think we live in a hologram
if yes are we just following a
pre-written script okay
what is this
holographic principle what is that
um
well it's it's a in a way it's really
hard to explain what the holographic
principle is i would have to
explain what is conformal field theory
and t d sitter conformal field theory
duality ada cft correspondence all that
but let's not go into that let me give
you a
an analogical briefer simpler possibly
hopefully simpler explanation um
i'm you've all heard of black holes
uh according to a black hole is a
quantum
object as well as an object that uh
that arises out of general relativity
right
uh
so a block a black hole is an object
that has an event horizon a boundary of
no return you go beyond that you will
never ever come out
so stay out of it right don't go
anywhere near a black hole firstly that
is that
secondly a black hole has an event
horizon the point of no return the
boundary of no return
inside
if you go inside the event horizon if
you cross the if you cross the
forbidden threshold then inside the
black hole you have empty space that's
what it is believed to be from the
perspective of general relativity you
have empty space more or less
but if you go inside the black hole you
keep going towards the center of the
black hole and
as you reach the center the strength the
the force of gravity the curvature of
space-time becomes more and more extreme
and at the very center you have what's
known as this singularity it's a
monstrous
thing
object
which
is in
infinitesimally small it's a point
which has
infinite curvature of space-time and
infinite density so as you go towards
the center of the black hole you get
stretched out in the process called
spaghettification
and at the center you get squeezed out
of existence
and you become you you disappear
but your mass energy gets added to the
mass energy of the black hole that's
what happens now
you as a physical human being
are made of particles and molecules and
bonds and all that that is a whole lot
of information quantum information
right
let's even if it's just a piece of let's
see if it's a human being or or an atom
or whatever goes inside it has certain
information that's encoded within it
when this atom or this human being gets
sucked into the black hole and gets
squeezed out of existence at the center
in the singularity
the mass energy does get added to the
mass energy of the black hole but the
information disappears and that doesn't
make any sense because throughout the
universe from all our understanding of
the laws of physics and of nature
information
is never destroyed
and yet apparently inside a black hole
information gets destroyed that is the
black hole information paradox
and stephen hawking said that
so that's what he said he did a lot of
work on black holes from the general
relativistic perspective from a quantum
perspective also quantum field theory
perspective a semi-classical hawking
radiation you may have heard of and so
on
so stephen hawking uh said that when it
comes to black holes when something goes
inside a black hole the mass energy is
added to the black hole but the
information is destroyed which makes no
sense so the string theory started
working on it so this is through
indulgent string theory an interesting
pastime
just kidding so string theorists
started working on it from the 1960s 70s
80s 90s in the 90s
this new principle was put forth and it
was eventually called the holographic
principle it said that any object that
crosses the event horizon
leaves behind its information
on the event horizon
this information
which is part of the object becomes
encoded it becomes smeared out smeared
out on the surface of the black hole on
the essentially essentially on the event
horizon
right so the information is not
destroyed the object gets destroyed its
mass energy gets added to the black hole
but its information remains encoded
remains encoded stays encoded on the
surface on the exterior boundary of the
black hole which is essentially a two
dimensional boundary
right so that essentially
says that the boundary of a black hole
is like a hologram it's a
two-dimensional surface which shows you
something that's three-dimensional
inside
what's a hologram like when you have a
credit card there is a holographic image
on that right as a security measure it's
a flat two-dimensional image but if you
switch from different angles it looks
like it has something three-dimensional
encoded inside
so a hologram is a two-dimensional
surface that gives you
information that that has information
that appears to be three-dimensional
inside
so there are two holograms and false
algorithms i will not go into that
so
if you expand if you extend this idea
the analogy of the black hole in
information being encoded on the surface
to the entire universe
then
our universe if it is finite it would
have
a boundary
and maybe
all of the information within the
universe such as me what what what's in
me what's in you
all of this all the stars planets
galaxies everything all of this
information
may well
be encoded on the surface on the
external surface that surrounds our
entire universe
so maybe our universe if some
great
alien being were to see it from outside
it would appear like a hologram a
two-dimensional surface
which encodes three-dimensional
information
within
so that is the holographic principle
that's the analogy i can offer you i
hope it makes sense so our universe
could very well be a hologram
and all the information within it could
be possibly encoded
in binary form or whatever form on a
two-dimensional surface that envelops it
from the outside
so that is
the holographic principle it arises out
of string theory
right
uh it was a gerard tooth who came up
with this
initially then it was uh
lennox kind of worked on it and and
other people as well
so that's what it is do we know if it's
true or not we don't know but from the
string theory perspective it makes sense
that's the simplest uh explanation i can
offer now the last quest part of the
question is are we following a
pre-written script
um
see
we all know the best theory of the
origin of the universe is what we call
what is colloquially called the big bang
theory
which says that all of the mass energy
information everything of the universe
was once compressed into a single point
or something that was close enough to a
single uh zero dimensional point the
initial singularity that eventually out
of which space time expanded and that is
what we call the big bang
now if this is true then everything that
happens in the universe can be uh
if you reverse time if you reverse the
equations of time we can go back to the
origin of the universe
and again if we take the time clock
forward then we can work everything back
forward in time which means that the
entire universe
all the mechan all the mechanics
dynamics statics of all the objects
molecules everything in the universe
atoms sub-atomic particles photons
everything
follows differential equations
and these are very complex differential
equations but they are simply
differential equations so they will work
forward in time and backward in time
if i mean this is how it makes sense
that's the best theory that we have and
according to this theory
there are certain uncertainties quantum
uncertainties in the universe the
heisenberg uncertainty uncertainty
principle says that the universe is
is uncertain it's probabilistic
it is not entirely deterministic and yet
these are actual uncertainties these
cannot be factored into the equations
if you remove this randomness from the
universe then everything else follows
the
differential equations all objects in
the universe subatomic particles
everything follows this differential
equation they are governed their entire
life cycle the the movement everything
is determined and governed by these
differential equations which means that
free will doesn't exist
what i am saying right now was
determined at the um at the moment of
the big bang the very
fact that i exist here was predetermined
at the moment
of the so-called big bang
and every single thing i speak
and i do
is predetermined
per these
differential equations that govern our
existence which means the thoughts that
i have the emotions that i have
everything is predicted determined
so from that perspective there is no
free will and everything is just the
universe is made up of clockwork there
is this randomness the quantum
randomness but that is
you can say it's an external kind of
thing
it is not something that can be
predicted
so beyond the fact that we have quantum
randomness everything else is
predetermined
and
the quantum the quantum randomness
does not affect
our will
so so that's what it is it's a very
scary thought i mean obviously we
understand next to nothing of the
universe our best theories are actually
quite crude in rudimentary and primitive
we understand less than five percent of
the universe so we should not get
carried away and start saying that we
know everything and there is no free
will but from the best theory that we
have which is a very poor theory
actually
from that theory it appears that
it would appear like free will is an
illusion and everything is like
predetermined
but that may not quite be the case
because we only understand a very little
tiny bit of the universe and our
uh our understanding of the universe is
far far far from complete or correct
entirely so
that's what i can offer you and i hope
that makes sense
okay prasad says
um thank you sir thank you very much
appreciate it
nasa reinca recently did the dart
mission that will act as a full
planetary defense system to protect us
from potential asteroidal impact
what are your views on it and do you
think it will be effective irrespective
of the size of the asteroid
so uh
planetary defense from asteroid and
comet impacts is something that's taken
very seriously we know what's happened
multiple times in the past our good
friends the non-avian dinosaurs no
longer exist they're no longer with us
uh very sadly and they were wiped out by
a massive impact the uh chicholu impact
event about 66 million years before
today which
either fully or partially contributed to
that catastrophe that mass extinction so
it's something that is taken very
seriously by uh organizations like nasa
so what is this dart mission i think
it's called deflection of asteroids
something or the other um what is it
okay let's let's google it right why do
we want to speculate
let us google up the exact full full
form of dart
where are you sir google
here we are here we are what is dart
mission
d dot simply dart double asteroid
redirection test that's what it stands
for so that is the dart mission so it's
it's i believe something that's going to
happen
in
uh september it's it's already been
launched uh when was it launched it was
launched some time ago
okay it was launched in 2021 and the
impact is going to happen in september
this year september 2022. so what is
this thing
this is a spacecraft
that is designed to go and collide with
a double asteroid system
uh so it's a double stone system a large
asteroid which
and a small asteroid that are
gravitationally bound together so it's
like an asteroid that has a small moon
of its own and this dart spacecraft is
going to go and impact one of these
objects i believe the moon the smaller
object
so the smaller part of the system
or maybe not whatever it is you can look
it up so let me explain the principle
behind this
the exact specifics you can google it
and see it for yourself but let me
explain the principles behind this
so let's say you have an asteroid which
is a high risk
asteroid which means it's an asteroid
that in the future could collide
with the earth because its path
in the future could coincide with the
earth
at a later time which means the earth
and this asteroid could be at the same
time and place in the future
so that is a high risk asteroid let's
say you have a high risk asteroid which
has a significant probability of impact
with the earth maybe in 50 years maybe
100 years maybe in 200 years maybe in
six months hopefully not yeah let's say
you have an asteroid like this how do
you ensure it doesn't collide with the
earth
you can use a gravity tractor you could
use a color you could use possibly
nuclear weapons you could use an impact
there are multiple ways of doing this so
this is a test of one of the ways of
deflecting the asteroid so what happens
is this this asteroid typically would
have a mass of
between a billion and a trillion
kilograms it's a massive massive thing i
believe its
diameter is close to a kilometer that's
a massive object
this spacecraft would weigh about half a
ton 500 600 kilos something like that
it will travel at a certain velocity it
will go and impact this asteroid
the
impact of the spacecraft into the
asteroid will will
will impart a certain amount of momentum
to the
uh to the asteroid what is the formula
for momentum very simple m v squared p
equals mv squared right
so it's uh
the mass of the impactor multiplied by
the square of the square of the velocity
that's what it is so the higher the
higher the velocity the the greater the
momentum and so on
so this impact will impart a certain
amount of momentum to the asteroid and
it will change the velocity of the
asteroid by i believe a couple of
millimeters or four millimeters per per
second or something like that whatever
the the exact amount is it's a very
small
change
in the velocity
but also it's a vector quantity vector
it has direction so it will change the
velocity
by a very small amount
very you could call it a negligible
amount but if you take the the effect of
that and you
take it forward
for by a few months a few years few
decades then the trajectory of the
asteroid will have a significant change
and
it may you may be able to ensure that it
does not
collide with the earth a few years or
decades down the line
so
that small little impact could
eventually will will eventually end up
deflecting the trajectory of the
asteroid and ensuring that it does not
hit the earth so this mission
its objective is to test out
this uh this essentially this technology
we know it works it will work but we
want to see exactly how it works
what is the effect of the of the impact
because certain asteroids
we may believe they are very compact but
they are quite loose some some asteroids
are just piles of rubble the consistency
is like that of popcorn in a bowl you
know
there was this recent uh
reasonably recent experiment in which a
spacecraft
landed on an asteroid i think it was
asteroid bennu
and
they were shocked to discover this
asteroid is just is a very loosely held
together body
and its uh density is much lower than
what they had expected and it the the
very slow this very slow touchdown of
the spacecraft threw up a huge
wall of debris you know gravel and all
that
from the asteroid so
if an asteroid is not solid if it is
just loosely bound rubble then an impact
like this could potentially just go
through it and not
have much of an effect or deflective
effect on the asteroid so it is
important
to test these
these things out so that is the reason
why the dart mission has been launched
and it's going to
the the
impact is going to happen in september
this year and there is going to be a
flyby of a cubesat or something which
will actually uh give us visual images
of the impact so that's something very
interesting i look forward to it and
it will certainly be very exciting and
it will give us a lot of new information
that we did not have until
thus far interesting very interesting
okay karan says apart from string theory
which theories are
the other contenders for the theory of
everything for the theory of everything
which one do you think has the most
promise
well um
the standard model of physics
which does not
include
dark matter or dark energy
so the standard model of physics is the
best theory that we have thus far
it's it's it's been called as the theory
of almost everything
but obviously it's it's very deficient
because it can explain
only about
four or five percent of the matter of
the mass energy composition of the
universe and that too there are certain
loopholes in this theory and and uh
and yeah so it's not a perfect theory
it is an approximate theory it is the
best jigsaw puzzle the jigsaw assembly
that we have made thus far but it will
certainly be improved upon so it is it
has been called by some people as a
theory of almost everything the standard
model
uh the other
theory that is touted as the theory of
everything is the string theory there
are i believe five versions of super
string theory yeah five major versions
so that is touted as a theory for
as a potential theory of everything
then there is m theory the 11
dimensional m theory which uh brings all
of which which brings which which is an
outcome of string theory essentially
yeah
uh so that is the so m theory is a
potential possible theory of everything
then you have loop quantum gravity which
is uh
which it may be a very good
interesting theory or i have spoken
about this in the past i've gone into
detail what
lqg loop quantum gravity is there's a
small video clip on this channel look it
up if you want more details so loop
quantum gravity is another
candidate
for a theory of everything and then you
have
theories of gravity of quantum gravity
because you would need to reconcile
general relativity and and quantum
theory in order to have a theory of
everything so you have something like
causal sets which is an approach to
quantum gravity that
that attempts to reconcile the two and
so on so these are various
candidates for being the theory of
everything
uh i think loop quantum gravity shows
promise
so
uh if you were to ask me which is the uh
thing that the theory that has the most
promise maybe i would say loop quantum
gravity but obviously it is not the not
the final version of the theory it's not
a perfect theory it has it needs to be
worked on but it's certainly very
interesting
it says even time emerges out of quantum
form and quantum loops so yeah if you
want to know more look at check out
check out my video my my video on this
channel and in which i go into a little
bit of detail about what lqg is
so that is the brief answer to this
question
okay
so says what is ethanol blending and how
will it help us produce energy for
transportation
so what is ethanol blending let's first
talk about what is ethanol
ethanol is ethyl alcohol
what is the formula c2h
c2h6o i believe ethyl alcohol you have
methyl alcohol then your ethyl co and so
on and so on
so c2h6o is ethyl alcohol or it or
ethanol ethanol whatever you want to
call it right what is it it's just
alcohol it's it's the alcohol that
humans can consume
it's it it's the that the recreational
drug that is that is the essential
component of
beer and whiskey and all of that that's
ethanol right
so now this is a good
source of fuel
in a typical
fuel
engine
in your car
in your scooter vehicles motorcycles etc
we use petrol or diesel
as the fuel that is combusted to produce
energy and that's what drives the
vehicle that's that that's the mechanism
right so you can also use ethyl alcohol
in the same engines in the same motors
you can so instead of filling it your
tank up with
petrol
or gasoline or diesel or whatever it is
you could fill it up with alcohol ethyl
alcohol and it will work just fine
so
ethanol blending is when you
mix about 10 or so percent 10 20
whatever the ratio is
of of ethanol into your gasoline into
your into your petrol so what you get is
petrol with which has about 10 or 15 or
20 whatever percent of ethanol in it
it's a blended
fuel
and that's what
the government of india is trying to do
in order to offset carbon emissions and
all that so how do you produce ethanol
you produce it by fermenting uh
agricultural
agricultural essentially garbage
right
so typically when you how do you make
wine
how how has wine been traditionally made
let's say out of grapes you crush the
grapes you let them ferment for a few
days and then you distill the thing
that's the whole process and you get
ethanol you get the vine grapevine out
of it and then you age it for whatever
time that's the process
so
wine is produced which wine is
essentially ethanol it is produced by
fermentation fermentation of grapes
fermentation of hops fermentation of
potatoes if you want to make schnapps
and so on and so forth you could also
take leaves and compost no i mean leaves
or or
grass
or uh
sugarcane stalks out of which all the
sugar has been extracted all of that you
could ferment that
and produce ethanol
so you are
recycling agricultural waste product
products to create ethanol that's great
that is a green technology
so then you produce ethanol using that
process and you use it you blend it with
your regular gasoline with your regular
petrol or whatever and you
offer that
as fuel for vehicles so that is the
process of that is the principle behind
ethanol blending i believe the indian
government is
working on this
and so that's how that's what it is and
that's how it is it's something that
helps us produce energy
for transportation and it is something
that is
can be classified overall as a green
technology as a greenish technology it's
not entirely green it has a carbon
footprint but it's better i mean if you
if you are able to replace
the uh
requirement the need for
for petrol with
ethanol
then it's it's good for the planet
because you no longer have to extract
uh crude oil etc out of the planet and
it's it's all good so so that is the
principle and that that is what ethanol
blending is
okay gihan gen says can you please tell
in short
how anti-matter is made anti-matter
anti-matter
so first of all what is anti-matter
so anti-matter is a weird form of matter
antimatter particles
antimatter particles whether they are
so antimatter particles share the same
mass as their regular matter
counterparts
the qualities such as electric charge
and other charges
other quantum numbers are opposite
so for instance
we have electrons
in the regular world the anti-matter
counterpart of the electron is the is
the positron it has the same mass as the
electron but it has a positive charge
the electron the regular electron has a
negative charge the positron has the
same mass but a positive charge
similarly protons
regular protons
have a positive charge
anti-protons have the same mass as the
proton but they have a negative charge
the photon is the anti-particle of the
photon and and so on right so that is
what anti-matter is
when you take protons nt protons and
positrons you bring them together
if you if you make an anti
if you if you make a positron go around
an antiproton you get antihydrogen
and similarly you can create anti matter
uh anti atoms and so on so that is what
antimatter is now how do we create it
typically antimatter is created in
particle colliders particle accelerators
you take two
particles and you smash them together
this could be ions these could be atoms
this could be protons
whatever you take these
so let's say you have the large hadron
collider in certain geneva yeah so this
is a particle collector it's a particle
smasher you smash i believe protons
together
or whatever it is you smash them
together at extremely high velocities
very very very high velocities close to
the speed of light
and the outcome of these collisions is
is new particles because of this
enormous amount of extra energy that's
added to the particles right equals mc
squared
so the outcome the output of these
massively energetic collisions is
new particles and typically what we find
is that when we create such matter in
particle accelerators we get an equal
amount of matter and antimatter
so that is typically how antimatter is
created
and one could one can
so you need a perfect or close to
perfect vacuum first of all in these
particle colliders and then you would
want to you would
to to
store this antimatter which is created
you would need pro proper vacuum and
magnetic confinement so that the
antimatter
particles don't collide with the walls
of the walls of the
container the moment they collide they
come in contact with the walls of the
container they will annihilate
and just give off pure energy
so that's how you create antimatter but
it's interesting you should also know
this that your body our bodies they emit
antimatter so a person who weighs about
let's say 70 kilos
would emit about 160 170 positrons per
hour positrons your physical body emits
antimatter if you weigh about 70 kilos
would
you your body would emit about 67 160 to
180 positrons per hour where does this
come from it comes from the decay of
potassium 40 which is a naturally
occurring isotope
that you ingest
typically by eating bananas but also
from drinking water and eating food and
also from breathing so there is a
certain amount of
potassium 40
that is available present in food
in water in the air
and there's a lot of it
in bananas
yeah so if you have a truck full of
bananas that can set up geiger counters
so your body emits antimatter but a very
small amount of antimatter
isn't that fascinating
all right next question
sort of says
what is the possibility
collapse of the earth into the sun or
collapse of earth into the black hole of
our galaxy as the galaxy has a smile
shape towards the center alright so what
you're essentially asking is what is the
ultimate fate of the earth and
as i hope you know the ultimate fate of
the earth is
intrinsically tied to the ultimate fate
of our sun the sun is our apparent star
and everything revolves around the fate
of the parent star
so
the real question you may be you are
actually asking is what is the ultimate
fate of the sun in the solar system and
that includes the planets around it
so what's going to happen to our sun
the sun currently is your
small
average kind of
yellowish star yeah
in a very boring neighborhood of the
galaxy yeah
it's going to remain this way it was
born about four and a half or so billion
years ago
out of the remains of an older star
so the sun was essentially reincarnated
from the the debris
the the debris of an older star so in
about five
five billion years from today the sun
will become a red giant
a red giant
uh because of the fusion reaction
because of the way the fusion reaction
within the sun changes
so the sun is essentially a massive
fusion reactor what is fusing it is
fusing hydrogen
into helium right now that's what's
happening
eventually what will happen is that all
of the hydrogen
in the sun will be used up in this
fusion reaction hydrogen is being fused
into helium
once all the hydrogen is used up
the core of the sun will have to fuse
helium into carbon into heavier elements
like carbon oxygen etc and the last
stage is when carbon is fused into iron
and the thing is that when you have the
fusion when you have a fusion reaction
of elements with with mass numbers
greater than 26 what is the mass number
it's the sum of the protons and the
neutrons in the nucleus of that element
so when you have fusion of elements with
a mass number greater than 26
then this fusion reaction uses more
energy than is output from the reaction
that is essentially the death nail of a
star
right
so in the case of the sun the sun is a
small star it's not really massive so
what will happen with the sun is that
about in about five billion years the
hydrogen will be used up and the sun
will become
the outer layers of the sun will expand
and go outwards
it will become a red giant its diameter
will increase massively it will engulf
the orbit of mercury mercury will
disappear and be burnt
it will eat up venus it will also eat up
the earth it will engulf the earth the
earth will then be within the sun within
the sun inside the sun so that process
that that's gonna happen at around five
billion years from today
then there will be this phase of fusion
of helium into carbon which is a very
small phase about 10
million
or so years
eventually the outer layers of the sun
will dissipate the sun will no longer be
powerful enough to to hold them together
and the outer layers will just dissipate
and go outwards that it will eventually
become what's known as a planetary
nebula or something like that
then the at this stage the core of the
sun still exists but it's no longer
fusing it's just really hot because of
the history of the sun and it's mostly
made up of carbon
this is the white dwarf stage of the sun
so the sun will become white dwarf and
it will remain a white dwarf for
trillions of years and slowly slowly
cool down
at the end stage all the heat most of
the heat will disappear dissipate out
into the atmosphere into the environment
into outer space into vacuum
and what will be left behind is what's
called a black dwarf
what is a black dwarf
it's a giant
diamond crystal
giant diamond crystal because the last
stage is the fusion
of what to what
of helium into carbon
so at the end you have this massive
carbon
nucleus a massive ball of carbon and it
is extremely highly compressed because
of the gravitational forces so it's
diamond that is the allotrope of carbon
that will be left behind
so it's a giant diamond crystal that you
will have have at the end at the end of
after trillions of years so that is the
ultimate fate of the sun so what's going
to happen the earth will be engulfed
by the sun in about five billion years
from today
and it will be burnt burned out all the
atmosphere everything will disappear it
will be just a hot
rocky object
within the
eventual nebula that will form from the
death of the sun
right so that's that's how it's going to
be uh it will not be engulfed by the uh
it will not fall into the
black hole of the galaxy because of the
way gravity is
the black hole is not like a giant
vacuum cleaner it sucks everything
inside no
even if you have a black hole
that's going around the sun it will not
suck anything inside it's just a massive
object which follows the the
laws of physics
right and there could possibly be a
primordial black hole in orbit around
the sun possibly maybe that's what the
so-called planet nine or planet x is
this unknown thing that seems to be
there but we are not able to see it
maybe
it's a primordial black hole a smallish
black hole
that is going around the sun and that's
why it's not visible maybe or maybe it's
a planet that we still haven't found
because the solar system is vast it's
enormous
so that is the ultimate long-term fate
of the earth and the sun and the solar
system
right
akash says
it seems like a great deal of time has
passed since a big scientific
breakthrough has happened especially in
physics
it it's my is my observation correct and
if it is how is it possible because we
are we are far more advanced
technologically compared to the 20th
century because of engineering still our
perception of the universe hasn't
changed much scientifically speaking
uh your observation is correct akash uh
the last great breakthrough major
breakthrough in physics was inflationary
theory
inflation
cosmological inflation which
uh this theory was put forth i believe
in 1980 or 1981 by alan guth
so that was the last major
breakthrough in theoretical physics
which has been proven
by observational evidence we find
observational videos of this and that's
why it is an integral part of the big
bang inflationary cosmological model
right
lambda cdm and so on so uh that's the
last major breakthrough we have
experienced in physics before that every
year every decade there are major
breakthroughs right
in the 20th 20th century there were so
many breakthroughs in physics
the entire world was transformed and
revolutionized you had relativity
special relativity general relativity
then you have quantum physics
you have the rudimentary quantum theory
the discovery of the quantum nature of
the world and then
quantum theory took off
it took a few decades but then you had
quantum field theory then you had
particle physics then you were you had
the understanding of what what particle
physics really is the symmetries of
nature
uh the eight-fold path and so much more
then you had the electrolytic theory
and all that remains now is to
understand what gravitation is
so since 1981 there's been no new
breakthrough no new massive major
discovery we are still essentially where
we were
in 1981.
the 21st century was supposed to be was
hoped to be expected to be the century
in which we will finally figure out what
gravitation is we have not moved one
millimeter forward
since the 20th century in terms of our
understanding of what gravitation is
and all of the uh progress that's
happening is like you rightly say it's
because of engineering we are our
engineering prowess is what is uh taking
us forward technologically so we have
more and more computing power better
better computers we have more
miniaturized devices like smartphones
and all that
technology is progressing it's
engineering that is doing it but there
is no fundament there is no new
fundamental breakthrough in physics
the big questions are still they still
remain unanswered so that is what the
situation is right now we have hit a
brick wall and we are not going forward
why is it so
why is it so well there are multiple
reasons we are not thinking differently
if we are
facing this problem we have to change
our way of thinking we have to change
our approach to solving the problems we
can't just keep on doing the same thing
over and over again and hope for
something different that's the
definition of madness i believe isn't it
uh doing the same thing over and over
again and hoping for a different outcome
each time doesn't work so what's
happening right now
everybody
especially the west especially the us
is deeply deeply invested in string
theory
string theory has taken over every
single almost every single theoretical
physics department
most of the funding
is being
poured into research in string theory
and you see so many papers being
published every
every week every month every year
so many papers you will find being
published every single day you can see
them on the physics archive
in other places
there is so much output research output
and yet it's taking us not one
millimeter further ahead so clearly
something is wrong
there is this attitude of publish or
perish in academia so the entire focus
is on publishing output volume
throughput but it's not taking us
forward
and the string theory mafia has choked
all progress essentially that's what is
happening that's what's happened for the
past many decades i am not trying to
disparage string theory but it has not
produced any results
it has not produced any results it's not
taken us forward it's produced wonderful
papers and beautiful mathematics and
very complicated mathematics and all
that but it's not taking us forward
in physics
so maybe
not maybe definitely it's time to
rethink our approaches we need funding
in other fields of physics
in other branches of physics in other
approaches
right
uh so that's that's where we are the
string theory of the string theory mafia
essentially
has uh
ensured that we are at this impasse
right now
so yes your observation is indeed
correct and we need a change of approach
totally right now it's all group think
just do the same thing over and over
again everybody must do string theory
otherwise you don't get funding you
don't get admission for your phd and all
that
that's how it is in the u.s so that's
why i say that the string theory mafia
has taken over it this is a stranglehold
you want to do a phd in theoretical
physics most likely you have to go into
string theory that's how it is you want
to take some other approach
you won't get
funding and
you won't be accepted that's how it is
so that needs to change
maybe things can change in other
countries
maybe if we in india could
could get get our act together and
reform the education system maybe we
could throw up a few breakthroughs but
we are far from doing that right now
so that is the situation
how does a wounded organism
regenerate to exactly the same structure
it had before
well it doesn't regenerate to exactly
precisely the same structure but
essentially the same structure
so let's say
we know how it is right
um
so why is it so how does the body know
that it has to regenerate exactly to the
same
in a certain way how does it know it is
because of the information that's
encoded in our genome in the dna the dna
is a blueprint
the dna is the blueprint to the entire
organism
as to how the protein should code what
proteins should code and what should
happen
so uh so that it's because of the
information that is passed on from
generation to generation encoded in the
genome in the dna
of the organism so when the organism is
wounded let's say it loses some some
part of the body
let's say it's a microscopic organism or
multicellular organism low lower life
form it knows how to regenerate and the
regeneration is done
because of the information encoded in
the dna even some uh species of lizards
like salamanders etc even if they lose a
limb
they can regrow the limb
and it the new limb that is regrown
after a few months or weeks or whatever
it is time period is is essentially the
same as the limb that was lost
so it is because of the genetic
blueprint provided in the genome in the
dna that is how
the tissues the organs
know i mean the the body the physiology
knows how to
uh to regenerate the tissue in what form
it is to be regenerated it is all
because of dna dna is the blueprint
of the organism
okay two questions in one arnov says ha
arnab says
was the first moon landing done by the
us during the space race era cold war
era real or fake
they just says why do many people still
believe in the flat earth theory and
also why do many people believe that
nasa's first moon landing was fake
okay
the first part of the question is was
the moon landing real or was it faked
well
india's chandrayaan mission has taken
pictures of the surface of the moon
which show
that the apollo lander is still present
on the surface of the moon right
it shows the tracks of the of the
astronauts who walked around and other
artifacts from that moon landing so
clearly
unless the chandrayaan
spacecraft is also fake unless it is
obviously it's not fake right
so clearly it really happened the other
thing look at it this way
we know
we know for certain that the american
government invested
two or three percent of the entire
nation's gdp
in the 1960s into nasa
we know that for a fact
a huge amount of money was poured into
nasa we know that it employed so many
scientists and engineers
we know that
right we also know that they built so
many rockets
the mercury program the gemini program
and eventually the saturn rocket the
saturn program
we know that these rockets were built we
have seen we still have footage of the
launches many of the initial uh tests
failed many of them ended in explosions
and disaster some of them actually went
into into earth orbit eventually they
you had a manned space place space
flight program we know it happened there
is enough evidence of the fact that
these rocket launches these human space
flights happened
we have
video footage ample amount of video
footage of all of these events
right
we also know
that they built the apollo rockets the
saturn rockets
saturn 5 the most powerful rocket ever
built until the time
we know that
we have seen the space launches
so we
know all of these things happened but if
they have invested so much time effort
and money and manpower to do doing this
and they have rockets that actually work
then why is it so hard to imagine they
actually worked and went to the moon
then we also have photographic evidence
of the moon landings
not just by the americans but by also by
the indians
by the indian
chandrayaan mission
so if you take all of this evidence
together i mean the only conclusion is
that this actually happened
right
so yes obviously this is this is real
these the moon landings were real they
were not faked
that is
my understanding if somebody has a
better understanding please feel free to
educate me in the comments i'm i have an
open mind all right now the other
question is by they just why do people
many people still believe in flat earth
theory and the moon landing was fake and
all that look
um consider this analogy
consider this energy analogy from
marketing and human psychology
people make a decision
to buy something
based on emotions
the purchase is made emotionally
and after you purchase the item you
justify it with logic
that is how the human mind works
so
people most people don't have an
understanding of a deep understanding of
science
most people because of the education
system because it's so hard to study
science it's it's hard to invest so much
so much time studying the science
studying science the scientific method
and so on so most people
rely on their understanding
rely on other people for their
understanding of science
so they choose somebody
an influencer a popular
media figure a writer whatever
they choose somebody business emotion
that yeah this person
feels good to me when i listen to this
person he or she looks like
he or she makes sense or maybe i like
that person's voice or maybe like the
person's face that person appears to be
trustworthy so you first form an
emotional connection with that person
and then you take then once you have the
emotional connection
you essentially uh start believing
everything that they say is is true
uh or it could be a book you like the
style of the book or whatever so most
people
they don't understand science
and then but they want to know about it
so they rely on intermediaries they rely
on middlemen
to give them information about science
in an easy to digest manner and many of
these
middlemen are
not quite correct
in the way they interpret science maybe
they do it on purpose maybe they do it
because they sincerely believe it's true
whatever the interpretation is
that is why many people believe in flat
earth theory and believe that the nasa
moon landing was fake and there are
religious reasons for that too many
religious figures especially in the
abrahamic religions
they they still propound the flat earth
theory that all of this is wrong and all
that and people who are religiously
inclined who derive
emotional uh comfort etc from religion
they will be very much predisposed to
believing everything wholesale
so these are a number of factors
why people believe such things flat
earth theory fake moon landings all of
that
most people uh don't have the
um
the intellectual
background the scientific training
required
to discern what's right from what's
wrong and what
what data is telling you as as opposed
to what data doesn't tell you so these
are the reasons why you have these
attitudes and these beliefs that still
persist as of today
but the thing is in india there are very
few people who believe in the flat earth
theory it's in the west in the us
etc that lots of people believe in flat
earth theory now ask yourselves why why
is it so
that is homework go ahead and what do
you think let me know in the comments
not in the chat in the comments once
this stream is done
all right next
swapnil says since pluto crosses
neptune's orbit
astronomers have long wondered why don't
the two celestial bodies collide
some simulations predict that pluto
should have collided with neptune or
escaped the solar system so what's
keeping pluto stable in its technically
chaotic orbit
gravitational mechanics celestial
mechanics right
the data that we have is data from the
past couple of centuries
past 50 years past 100 years
the indian astronomical data that was
transmitted to the west maybe
may have
spanned a period of five thousand or
maybe a few few more thousand years
that's an eye blink of time in the
cosmological scale in the scale of the
lifespan of the solar system so the
truth is
that
many of the orbs that we have in the
solar system today could be unstable
orbits
it is almost a certainty
that the orbits have changed that many
ancient protoplanets that were once in
orbit around the sun would have been
ejected out of the solar system many of
them would have collided the asteroid
belt is tested is testimony to an
ancient collision in which
two or more
uh
proto planets or ancient planets
collided and got destroyed
the fact that saturn has rings is
testament to such violent uh to such a
violent event uh it's possible that
earth was struck
by an ancient planet and that gave rise
to them
gave birth to the moon
and so on
it's also known that the orbit of
jupiter has changed over time that's
what the best simulations tell us and
that's why it's it's able to shield the
inner planets from
massive collisions with asteroids
and
we know that the orbit of the the axis
of rotation of uranus i believe or
neptune i think uranus is is tilted at
98 degrees which is again
the consequence of an ancient collision
with some other object
we know that
the moon triton
is something that's been captured
because of the an unstable orbit
and it is also known that pluto crosses
the orbit of
uranus neptune one of the most likely
neptune
so that also is is in a tilted and
strange orbit now pluto takes about 247
years to complete one orbit around the
sun for earth it is 365 days for pluto
is it is 247 earth years
so
the solar system is still a dynamic
place
the orbits are still evolving
in a few million years
it is possible that the orbits may have
changed again
it's possible that venus may be ejected
out of the solar system in a few million
years
we only have a very small snapshot of
time
of for which we have data and
information
these processes happen over millions and
billions of years
so in the future pluto may very well
collide with neptune
it may very well escape the solar system
even venus possibly may escape the solar
system or may even collide with the
earth
these things are very very possible but
over a very long period of time
it won't all happen in our lifetimes our
lifetimes are
are an eye blink of time
what is a hundred years it's nothing in
the cosmological scale
so uh so that's the that's the answer
these things this is all still happening
in a few million orbits
in the future pluto may may end up
somewhere else it may end up colliding
with neptune it may end up escaping the
solar system and all these things all of
these options are still very much open
yeah so we what we are seeing is is a
moment frozen in time our lifespans are
so small that what we are seeing is just
a few moments in time that's it but the
whole story is much much much longer
than that
right it's like you're watching a movie
for three seconds and you're asking why
did nothing happen
you get it so that's how it is
okay raise says
how can a human life be extended and can
it be done in this century please shed
some light on this this is the age old
quest
of immortality or longer life how can we
live longer can we live longer can we
live 100 years can we live 150 years 200
years wouldn't that be great
so can human life be extended so to
answer this question we have to ask
ourselves why do humans uh die it's
because of the process of aging
eventually aging deteriorates the body
to a certain extent that it cannot
sustain life right
so that is death by natural causes so
so how do you
slow
aging if slow aging then certainly you
can extend human life right
so let's say aging happens at a certain
rate
dx by dt
let's say you
make that rate half so one half of what
it was then you may be able to double
your life span
or something like that so what causes
aging it is believed that one of the
primary contributors to the to the
process of aging
is the shortening of the telomeres in
human chromosomes
so
human chromosomes are what make up our
dna in our in the nuclei of cells not
red blood cells but other cells
and at the ends of chromosomes you have
these structures called telomeres
these telomeres when you're born have a
certain length
and as you grow older the telomeres
their length
gets
progressively shortens
and it is believed that it is the
shortening of the telomeres that causes
the process of aging
and therefore one of the keys
to slowing down aging or maybe even
reversing it could be ensuring that
this process of the shortening of the
telomeres doesn't happen or maybe
figuring a way out to reverse it or stop
it
so there is a lot of research being done
about this i believe there are
i don't remember the names but there are
some scientists some very prominent
scientists biologists etc who are
working on this
so that is the primary approach that i
know of as of today that people are
taking towards
the
science of possibly how to
reverse or or slow down aging and that
would obviously
have the consequence of extending human
life spans
so it could happen
this century uh conceivably that is the
best answer i can offer you uh
uh do your own research it's it's in
it's an interesting field and that also
has other questions that pop up from
that i mean
is the human brain capable of
functioning well beyond a certain age
you may have a body that stops aging
will it also stop the deterioration of
the human brain of the human mind
dementia senescence or whatever you call
it right
um
so yeah these questions are still
unanswered but work is being done on
this
okay karan says where is voyager now
does it still send any data so voyager
is not one thing it's not one spacecraft
there are two two spacecraft voyager 1
and voyager 2. strangely enough voyager
okay i think voyager 2 was launched
before voyager 1 uh a month or so apart
so both of these spacecraft were
launched in 1977
and the objective the purpose of these
two spacecraft was to photograph the
inner the the gas giant planets of our
solar system
saturn jupiter uranus neptune
essentially end their moons if possible
so these were great successes
both of these spacecraft did a great job
of photographing giving us the first
good photographs
of these
gas giant planets beautiful photographs
that people still put as their
wallpapers and all that yeah so uh
that was the original objective of the
voyager spacecraft
um so as of today i believe voyager 1 is
roughly
150 or so astronomical units away from
the sun from the earth
what is an astronomical unit it is the
distance between the sun and the earth
that mean distance is called one
astronomical unit so as of today 2022
voyager 1 is about 150 between 150 and
160 astronomical units away from where
we are
that is
about 23 billion kilometers
from here
so that is where voyager is as of today
it is now technically in interstellar
space it has technically
left the solar system
it's now in interstellar space it is
still sending back data and that data
has helped us understand a lot about how
about what the
environment of interstellar space is
like
what is the termination shock like of
the solar system what is that uh
so all of these uh various regions of
space we have been able to understand
them better because of the data that
voyager 1 and 2 have sent back to us it
is still
sending us data
but
um the power supply on this spacecraft
on on voyager 1 is now
failing
it will probably fail by 2025.
which means that this spacecraft will
most likely stop sending us data stop
collecting and sending us scientific
data
by around 2025 which will which means
that we will no longer be in contact
with it
from that point onwards from that point
onwards it's a dead spacecraft more or
less
it will go off into interstellar space
for
tens of thousands of years millions of
years
and maybe someday somebody out there may
find it
and figure out where it came from
so that's what it is it it contains this
gold disc with the
information about where the earth is and
there are recordings of voices from
from
from the our planet and all that so
there is
a certain amount of data on it
in the hope that somebody out there
may find it someday
so that's where voyager is that is a
status and
yeah that's your answer
your favor says in the future can
technology remove the uses of ink pen
and pencils yes certainly technology can
do anything
technology could uh do away with the
requirement for using pens and pencils
today we have these touch screens you
could actually write stuff with your
finger on it or you could use a stylus
like the apple styles or apple pen
whatever whatever they call it there are
such devices available for android as
well and so on right
so yeah you may no longer need the need
ink pens and pencils you may no longer
need paper and so on
so technology can certainly do it but is
it something that will
gain wide acceptance will everybody have
the money to shell out
the the large amount of money that you
need to shut out for to to acquire such
a device is it going to be practical is
it something that will be able to be
adopted
widely by everybody all across the world
these are questions that still remain
sometimes technology takes things too
far which you don't really need
let me tell you an interesting story
so in the 1960s the americans and this
1950s 1960s and 1970s the americans and
the soviets had this massive space race
right
they were both wanting to be the number
one space fading nation on the world
because of various considerations
including military technology
space has a military dimension so on
so the americans and the russians were
competing for supremacy in the space
race
and the americans said astronauts the
russians the soviets had cosmonauts yuri
gagarin was the first cosmonaut
valentina tereshkova was the first woman
in space
neil armstrong was the first human being
on the moon and so on right
so they had this space race many years
later when things were better when the
cold war was more or less over
um
one of the american astronauts met a
russian astronaut and they had a
conversation they exchanged notes and
experiences and all that and the
american guy
i think it was neil armstrong if i'm not
mistaken
he asked the russian guy about how did
he write in space
the american guy said that we in nasa we
had this massive uh
research program in in as to how to
how to uh
create a pen how to build a pen that
works in space the ink should flow the
way it flows on earth and you should be
able to write in space
so it cost the entire technology create
the demonstration and creation had it
cost millions of dollars and eventually
they were able to create a pen that
worked flawlessly in space
yeah
so so the american astronaut asked the
russian guy how did you guys
write in space
the russian guy said we used a pencil
no need to spend invest millions of
dollars
developing
a pen with ink that works in space they
just used pencils
they solved it
this
this problem with low tech with a low
tech
solution so yeah that's an anecdote but
uh
you don't need to remove everything and
and invest in uh in
expensive technology to to replace
things that don't really need
replacing
of course pen paper paper is a problem
the more humans we have the more paper
is required and the more trees you need
to cut there is definitely a problem but
which would need a solution
but overall uh
to use technology to get rid of pens and
in pencils
seems as of today a little bit of
overkill
okay alpha says can you briefly tell
about saturn's hexagon so why should i
tell something when i can show you a
picture a picture is worth a thousand
words
okay saturn let's go to saturn
pigs are gone
so
there you are
it's something that's on the polar
regions of saturn
this massive hexagonal arrangement of
the clouds of the of the top
top layers of the saturnian saturnine
saturnian atmosphere
this is the shape it's it's a reasonably
hexagonal shape as you can see there are
vertexes at the center and there are
other storms as well within the hexagon
this is another
image of that
and you can see various representations
of the hexagon and this red image here
is
the central vertex within the hexagon
right this is another
image of that in different colors
so this is the hexagon saturn's hexagon
now what is it
it is something it is a certain shape
okay hexagonal shape that has emerged
out of the
complex fluid mechanics and dynamics of
the saturn atmosphere
it's something that seems to
exist
on the top layers of the atmosphere
because of the complex interplay of the
various gases that various kinds of
gases that are there in the atmosphere
they would exist at different
temperatures
and they would mix in certain ways
so this is a consequence of the fluid
mechanics of the saturnian atmosphere
fluid mechanics is an extraordinarily
complex field
the equations that govern fluid
mechanics are they look deceptively
simple
but they are incredibly difficult to
solve
typically you need uh
you need super computer simulations and
all that
so i don't have the exact answer as to
why you have a hexagonal shape there
but it is because of the interplay of
the various fluids and gases in the
atmosphere which has given up
given
thrown up this sort of shape and
i believe various uh scientists in
certain universities have tried to
replicate this sort of
uh phenomenon
and some of them may have succeeded
so it's a consequence of the of the
complex fluid mechanics in the
atmosphere of saturn which involves the
various
various gases of the atmosphere
various compositions
various mixtures various
various
temperatures
various densities and all that you take
all of these various different
parameters together
in a planet of a certain size and you
and
it throws up this sort of
uh geometrical shape
when it comes to other planets you have
different trip you don't have any
hexagon on the earth's atmosphere you
don't you don't ever see that at the
poles right
but for instance when you take some a
body like titan titan is a moon of
saturn it has a very thick atmosphere
on titan at the poles you have these
vertices
the the
titan's atmosphere is very thick it's
composed of hydrocarbons it's a very
cold atmosphere but very thick and at
the poles of titan you have these
vertices which are like roughly
uh
what's the shape called spiral kind of
shapes yeah
so it's a smaller much smaller object
and you have spirals there but on a gas
giant like saturn you have a hexagon
which you don't see on jupiter again so
it's it's a very complex phenomenon to
which we have no ready answer
but the basis of this com of this
phenomenon is fluid mechanics
okay abhijit varma says atoms never
touch each other
for if they ever did there would be a
huge explosion
then what creates a sensation of touch
what creates cause and effect when a
billiards ball hits another another one
when raphael hits a forehand
okay so uh
if two atoms were to collide you would
not
really have an explosion what happens is
the
is governed by nuclear physics and
within that there is quantum mechanics
and so on so that's a different topic so
what what causes the sensation of touch
what is what is the what is behind the
cause and effect sequence of a billiards
ball bouncing off another one and all
that the real question you're asking
is why does
matter
occupy space
why does matter occupy space why is it
solid why is it reactive
and so on and the final the the
principle at the at the heart of this
is what's called the pauli exclusion
principle so what is the pausing
exclusion principle it's
it's something that is part of quantum
mechanics quantum physics the pauli
exclusion principle says that two or
more identical particles with half
integer spins that is fernions cannot
occupy the same quantum state within a
single quantum system simultaneously at
the same time
okay
it's about fermions particles with half
integer spin what are fermions fermions
include all the quarks all the leptons
all composite particles made up of these
uh made up of an odd number of these
such as baryons atoms nuclei and so on
these are fermions and because they
cannot occupy the same quantum space
this quantum state simultaneously within
a single quantum system that's why
matter takes up space that's why matter
occupies space that's why you cannot
squeeze matter beyond a certain limit
unless you want to create a singularity
that's possible beyond a certain uh that
that is generality that's a whole
different thing
but that is the reason why matter
occupies space that is why matter is
hard or soft or whatever depending on
the properties
it is all because of the pauli exclusion
principle
right
atoms can touch each other they can
merge together in the process called
fusion that's a whole different story
but the reason why matter occupies space
and the reason why you have the
sensation of touch and the sensitivity
of the cause and effect thing of
billiards balls bouncing and all that it
is all because of the the at the heart
of all of these phenomena is the pauli
exclusion principle of quantum mechanics
so you can explore that further
that's what i can tell you in brief
um
alpha says when humans discovered
nuclear fission and fusion
they cleared they created weapons rather
than using that energy to power machines
is this the greatest stupidity of
mankind
when humans
discovered fire
they used it for cooking they also used
it for warfare
when humans discovered metals
coppers melting iron smelting they used
it
for building utensils for for building
various things and also for building
swords and knives and weapons
all technology has multiple uses
when humans discovered nuclear fission
they
built nuclear reactors
that can be used to produce
energy electricity
but they can also be used to to
develop nuclear weapons so that's just
how it is
technology
is purpose agnostic
technology just exists but how you use
it is up to you
ideally you would want to use all
technology for good purposes
non-destructive non-military purposes
but that's not how the world works
so is it stupidity well if that is the
greatest video of stupidity of mankind
then then humankind is stupid by nature
inherently and so are our closest
relatives the chimpanzees who are also
just as inherently violent and stupid as
we are
so technology is purpose agnostic you
can use it for whatever purpose you want
a stick can be used for
playing drums it can be used for
cracking skulls i mean that's up to you
right
so yeah i mean there's no value judgment
in this that's just the way we are as a
species
and all technology can be used for a
variety of purposes including
destructive purposes that's just the way
it is
secret santa says i would like to know
what is your opinion on the feinman
lectures books
is it a good book to understand physics
for beginners or the fundamentals of
physics recommended by you is a better
option
uh
the feignman lectures are obviously a
series of books written by the great
richard feynman the great physicist
richard fehmann feynman who was a nobel
laureate
these books
they are
well they they are
people say that these are books for
beginners but that's not the case
these books
should be used by
by elite level students
the top one percent of the students
it is not something that is suitable for
beginners even though they may be uh
portrayed as beginner level books
the fundamentals of physics by halliday
and rustic or whatever else
is the standard text that is used in
schools and colleges etc that is the
right
place to start if you want to learn
physics from scratch
the the fundamentals of physics by faith
the feynman lectures
show is something that that should be
studied by elite level students the top
one percent
that's
only when you have mastered the
fundamentals
can you go into the finance lectures and
then you will understand the
fundamentals even better from a
different perspective from the
perspective of a genius physicist
so when i was a kid
i tried studying the feynman lectures
as as a beginner text did not work for
me i had to go down to the level of
halide rusnik study that thoroughly
mastered that internalizat that
thoroughly by solving lots of problems
then later on when i
reopened the feynman lectures they made
a lot more sense to me
right so it is not for beginners it is
not even for
ordinary students it's for elite level
students that is my perspective on this
they just says
until the 10th standard i was a science
enthusiast but due to my jee preparation
i hate science now what should i do to
restore my love towards science
hmm that's an interesting question
let me give you a strange
example
let's say your favorite food
is pizza pizza yeah
let's say your favorite food is pizza
you love it more than anything else
now what if
i were to force you
to eat nothing but pizza
not twice or thrice a day but six times
a day
for an entire year
let's say one of these days you feel
like eating
masala dosa with sambar
i say no
you want that taste you need to have
that on a pizza masala
sambar flavor on pizza let's say one day
you feel like having
aloo gobi i said no you want that you
need to have that on pizza aloo gobi
flavor on pizza with the aloo gooby
toppings
let's say you want palik paneer i say
you must have it on pizza palak paneer
topping on pizza so i force you to eat
pizza six times a day and nothing but
pizza six times a day for 365 days
continuously
after after after a year will you still
love pizza
will you still think it's your favorite
food no you'll be sick and tired of it
right
so that is the kind of thing that
happens when you force somebody to do
something that they love even they may
love it but you force them to do it over
and over and over again for a long
period of time they will get tired of it
no matter what it is
so maybe you love science and why why
does somebody love science because
you're fascinated with science you find
it fascinating and you want to learn it
and you want to go to the next level in
the next level the next level you want
more and more knowledge because it's so
interesting but when you are doing when
you're preparing for an exam you're not
learning anything new you are staying at
the same level but you are practicing
over and over again problem after
problem after problem
and all you are trying to learn is how
to
get good marks in an exam
it's no longer about loving the subject
it's just about passing an exam
that kind of kills the joy of learning
the subject now don't get me wrong i'm
not saying you should not study for
exams it is a necessary part of life
unfortunately the way the education
system is today you have to get to pass
exams and you have to get good marks and
get a certain ranking or whatever
because that's how you get a degree or
admission and that's how you get a job
eventually that's just the way the world
is certain things you have to do but yes
it can kind of kill all the joy
of the subject of
the the joy and the fascination that you
had for the subject
so
let's say i forced you to eat pizza for
six times a day for a year how will you
rediscover your love for pizza by taking
a break for it for a while so let's say
you have done your jee you got a good
good good ranking you got you got
admission to your iit or whatever then
take a break for a while before you you
have to go and join the iit just
detoxify your mind of that
do something else so that would
typically be how you do it
uh but if you had a love for science
inherently
then i think you can certainly restore
it after a while
you you just need to ensure that the
burnout stage
is is behind you in the rear view mirror
so that's what i would offer to you
there is no hard and fast rule of how to
rediscover your love or restore your
love
typically you take a break from
something for for some time
and then you can
recharge your mind and maybe hopefully
rediscover your love for the subject
so typically it's like this
when you are doing research you you're
always learning something new you're
trying to discover something that
nobody has discovered thus far
which means you're going deeper and
deeper into the subject but that is the
joy of discovery you may have to work
eight twelve hours a day every day for
five years ten years in in the in the
pursuit of what you're trying to
discover
albert einstein worked from
went
essentially he he disappeared from 1905
to 1915. in the quest of the general
theory of relativity it took him a
decade of relentless
hard work
he did not he did not
lose his love for physics because he was
doing it for from the purpose of
discovery
right he was every day he was making
some progress he was discovering
something new as long as that is there
you will not uh feel that your your
quest is pointless but when you're just
forced to study for an entire year for
an exam and you're not learning anything
new you're just practicing that can kind
of burn your mind out especially when
you have to do it like
eight or ten or twelve hours a day the
way some people have to do
so yeah when you are in that situation
the best remedy is to take a break
as long as you can possibly can
so that could possibly do the trick for
you
shubham says i will be in a graduate
program for mathematics from fall 2022.
how should i choose one area of research
in mathematics
as of now i like algebra like
algebra and representation theory
functional analysis and algebraic number
theory however i have not been able to
decide one area for research i have
funding available for six years and i am
sure i won't be able to research on all
these topics within this time period
could you please advise me something so
that i can get out of this dilemma okay
so i will give you a general
rule of thumb as to how to do research
when you're starting off you are going
to go into graduate research graduate
program which is the master's level and
eventually it will culminate in a phd
right and you have funding for six years
so typically you would do a certain
piece of research for your master's
level requirements
uh and there'll be course work in that
and then for your gra for your phd you
will do
possibly a different uh kind of research
the rule of thumb is that when you are
starting off when you are in the in
graduate school don't
try to bite off more
more than you can chew which means
don't try to
tackle a problem or take on a problem
that will give you a nobel prize or a
field medal don't do that
don't take something that's massive and
very difficult take something that will
produce original genuinely original
research but it's not too hard and too
complicated
you just need to get your degree first
you need to to
reach that milestone once you get the
degree and then when you go further in
your career you can take up the bigger
problems
so don't take take on too many things
and don't uh
try to tackle enormous problems
keep it simple
make sure that the problem that you take
will
advance the field in some way will
ensure that you have done original
research but don't make it too difficult
and too complicated so that is the
simple rule of thumb that i would offer
you from a lot of experience
and and yeah
from my experience right
so that's the best advice i can offer
you simple advice all the best sir
ashish says is it easier to understand
other subjects if one understands the
hard sciences
uh
typically a person who understands
mathematics and logic can understand
anything
and the in the in the basis the
foundation of all the hard sciences
physics chemistry biology etc is
mathematics and logic
and the scientific method which is logic
right
so yeah who is it uh
nawal ramik ravikanth right the great
the the famous investor he says that if
you if you understand math and logic you
can understand and master
almost anything
and i totally agree with that that's
been my experience also and i realized
this quite late that yeah i can
i can understand lots of different
fields
because i have the advantage of of
knowing math
and physics
and the scientific method which is logic
so the short answer to your question is
yes it is indeed easier to understand
other subjects if one
has
a rigorous training and understanding in
the hard sciences yes it is indeed true
aloha says is it okay to breathe
i highly recommend
breathing yes i highly recommend it
okay with that we are at the end of
today's
questions that i have selected now let
us take uh
some questions from the chat
if you have questions
do ask me in the live chat right now
um um
okay shahil says if i don't get into iit
should i use mit open course where
computer science and engineering courses
or are there any better options
see
why do you get into the iit but or why
do you try that to
get a degree right you can certainly
learn the subject from mit open
courseware but you will not get a degree
at the end of the learning experience
uh so if you just want the knowledge if
you just want to master the subject
then i would certainly recommend the
open courseware uh series whether it's
mit whether it's stanford or whatever
else it's all available for free on
youtube great resource
even if you're in the iit and you if you
want to understand the subject from a
different perspective for or whatever
you could certainly
take that as something extra to study
but if you want a degree then you have
to get into an institution iit or
something else so that's the options
that you have
all right um
how to be a polymath like da vinci first
of all you need to be born extremely
intelligent genius level intelligence uh
very few people have that so if you have
that then you should
explore your curiosity and study
everything you can read as much as you
want as you can
essentially dedicate and invest your
entire time into learning
that's how you become a bollywood
polymath like leonardo da vinci he was
an engineer he was a painter he was an
artist he was a scientist
he
uh contributed significantly to the
field of anatomy so he had so many
different interests that is the
definition of a polymath somebody who
was who is
more than competent who who is an expert
in multiple
fields or subjects music art science
mathematics and so on
so very few people can be that you have
to be at a very high level of
intelligence and competence genius level
so that's the first requirement and then
you have to be curious and you have to
invest the time and the effort in
learning all of and mastering all of
these different
disparate disciplines that's how you do
it sir all the best
right
um what other questions
when will i show my bookshelf well you
can see some more of it now maybe maybe
in the future i will take some
photographs and just put it up
on the community section and you can
take a good deep look at it
all right
uh okay
johan are space hurricanes dangerous
i'm not quite sure what a space
hurricane is
i think it's some
kind of interaction between the solar
wind
with the magnetosphere of the earth
similar to the process that causes uh
i think that's what a space hurricane is
is it dangerous um
a space hurricane is is a
symptom of a larger cause i mean if
that's what it is
so what would really be dangerous is uh
is solar wind or or
yeah solar storm essentially because
that could uh
interact with the magnetosphere the
magnetic uh
environment of the earth
and it could potentially disrupt
electrical grids and other systems on
the earth that could cause a lot of
problems
so that is what i can offer you right
now i'm not quite sure what
what space hurricanes are
which phenomenon is now called space
hurricanes but how about i look into it
and maybe i can give you a more
in-depth answer next next time so yeah
okay any other questions
that would evoke my curiosity
what are white holes white holes i have
answered this question i think one or
two episodes before
white holes are essent you can think of
a white hole as a time reversed black
hole
so if you had a black hole in a black
hole everything goes inward inside
inside and there is a
an event horizon which is a point of no
return once any object any particle any
human being or whatever crosses the
event horizon
there is no way of them to re-emerge
from there it's the point of no return
if you were to reverse that process
then a white hole is like a time
reversed black hole it has an event
horizon
and it is the point of no entry beyond
that you simply cannot enter
so in a black hole you will see things
going inside
objects falling inside in a white hole
the gravitational effects are the same
but the white hole is the opposite of a
black hole things emerge out of it so
essentially a white hole is like a time
reversed black hole
right
constant change says exams exam skill
curiosity subjects what to do sir well
there is there is no
there is no remedy to it right now the
system the education system is such that
everything depends on exams exams are
high stakes things and you have to get
good marks and exams in order to well
achieve whatever great objectives you
have
i know they kill curiosity they kill the
joy of life they kill the joy of the
subject that's what it is
that's not how the system should be
a better system would be continuous
evaluation of a sub of a student's
performance throughout the year
not through exams but by other means
there are lots of other examples in
other countries that you could take a
look at
but as of now this is what we have
exams
have to be dealt with
so all i can say is deal with it and
once you are done with your exam take a
break
and hopefully that will recharge your
mind and then
your curiosity will be hopefully
brought back to where it was
that's that's all i can offer right now
okay do we have any other interesting
questions
how is
emotional intelligence necessary in life
i
you know i i like to define things
what is the definition of emotional
intelligence i don't have a definition
for that
so um
so the answer is i don't know i don't
know what it is first of all i know what
intelligence is is
it is the ability to learn things
rapidly and
and apply the learnings in solving
problems and dealing in in dealing with
life and situations and and problems
that is the rough
definition of what intelligence is now
what is emotional intelligence i don't
quite know i know people have written
books about that
i may even have a book somewhere lying
around about emotional intelligence i've
never read it
never made sense to me i mean i may have
started reading it but i i couldn't wrap
my my mind around it so
so yeah i don't quite know what it is
what i can say is
what is necessary in life is emotional
stability
most people are governed by their
emotions
a few sometimes they're happy and things
are great they can do things sometimes
they're upset and they cannot do
anything the plans change depending on
the emotions the agenda of the date
changes depending on how what your
emotional state is
so many people if not most people are
greatly driven and governed by their
emotions their emotions govern their
life
that is bad
if you are a person who is driven and
governed by emotions you will not
achieve much in life
you need emotional stability even when
you're feeling bad or good or whatever
the best thing is is a plateau of
emotions where you are you know
equanimous
so that comes through i don't know some
people are born with that some people
need training some people need
meditation some people need other things
but what i would say
is most important in life is emotional
stability don't allow your emotions to
drive you and govern you
right
okay any other questions
any other questions
one lecture on pyramids of egypt how is
it built
um
yeah
it's it's architecture it's technology
technology from that time a few thousand
years ago
so yeah i'm not quite sure how they
built it maybe it's a mystery
so yeah maybe i will look into it maybe
maybe yeah
maybe
okay
there are lots of questions about
history and geopolitics today is the day
of science my dear friends
um
uh okay i guess we are we are
i i guess i guess that's it for today
uh there are lots of questions but i'll
i'll call it call it quits
at this point nearly two hours so so
thank you
okay let's let's take one
one last question
which is is it a scientific question
sagnik says is it okay to not get
married married
well science has no opinion about this
so it's your choice it's your choice
whether you want to get married or not
it's your choice who am i to tell you
whether it's okay or not
it's for each person to decide for
themselves there is no right or wrong in
this
so i would say that if that is what
works for you if that is what makes you
happy then go ahead with that
go ahead with that you should go with
whatever is best for you from your
perspective all right
and with that
i will end today's session thank you
very much great talking to you all
and i will see you in tomorrow's history
geopolitics and current affairs
session until then take care
and see you bye